Speaker: Sidney Poitier was the first black person to win the Best Actor Oscar in 1964
for his performance in Lilies of the Field.
Denzel Washington was the second black man to win the Best Actor Oscar in 2002 for Training Day.
He described Poitier as ‘the man who opened doors for us that had been closed for years.’
Sidney Poitier was the youngest of seven children.
His parents were tomato farmers who worked in the Bahamas,
where they had no running water or electricity.
He was born two months early and nobody expected him to live.
His mother went to see a fortune-teller to find out if he would survive.
She said, ‘Don't worry about your son.
He will carry your name to many places.’
At 16, with no education, Sidney arrived in New York with only $3 in his pocket.
He tried to get a job as an actor, but the director told him, ‘Stop wasting your time.
Get a job as a dishwasher.’
He was married twice, to a dancer, with whom he had four daughters,
and to a Canadian actor, with whom he had two daughters.
In his 50 years in film, he starred in and directed 40 films.
He played many iconic roles,
including a young doctor in Guess Who’s Coming to Dinner and a teacher in To Sir, With Love.
He received many awards, including a knighthood from Queen Elizabeth II
and an Honorary Oscar in recognition of his ‘remarkable accomplishments as an artist and as a human being.’
Denzel Washington was born in New York.
His mother owned a beauty parlour, and his father was a church minister.
His parents divorced when he was 14, and his mother sent him to an expensive private school.
He later went to university and got a degree in drama and journalism.
At a time when Denzel wasn’t doing well at university,
a woman told his mother that she had a prophecy about her son.
She said that he ‘would travel the world and speak to millions of people’.
He has been married since 1983,
and he and his wife Pauletta have four children, two sons and two daughters.
He has played many Shakespeare roles since his early days as an actor, both in theatre and film,
including Lord Macbeth in Joel Coen’s 2021 film The Tragedy of Macbeth.
He has received many awards,
including an Oscar for Best Supporting Actor for his role in the film Glory.